A Guide to the Edgar E. MacDonald Papers 1933-1993
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Edgar E. MacDonald Papers 1933-1993
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 142
10 linear feet and 4 items
Edgar E. MacDonald
Administrative Information
Access
Access to the Roger Hunt Carroll correspondence is restricted. Consult with Archivist for further information.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the department by Dr. Edgar E. MacDonald in March 1990 and continuing.
Biographical/Historical Information
Edgar Edgeworth MacDonald was born in Richmond on 5 March 1919, the son of John Edgar and Marie Edgeworth MacDonald. He attended the University of Virginia (1936-1938), Sorbonne, University of Paris (1947- 1948), Richmond Professional Institute [VCU] (B.S.), University of Richmond (M.A.) and the University of Paris, D. de l'Universit鮠A professor of English at Randolph-Macon College from 1953 until his retirement in 1984, Dr. MacDonald is currently the Senior Cabell Scholar at Virginia Commonwealth University. He is the author of numerous articles and books, including a biography of James Branch Cabell published by the University of Mississippi Press in 1993.
Scope and Content Information
The materials in this collection range from 1654 to 1990 and include correspondence, articles, reviews, drafts of published work, photographs and clippings. The bulk of the material can be found in the 1970- 1980 date range. There is extensive information on James Branch Cabell, Ellen Glasgow and the Edgeworth/Mordecai relationship. Activities of the Ellen Glasgow Society and the Virginia Writer's Club, to a lesser extent, are also documented. Clipping for "Rain" RTD 10/31/24 fragile note taken and clipping discarded. Photographs removed to University Photograph Collection. The video "Richmond: Historic Sights & Haunts" has been transferred to RG 70.
Arrangement
Series I--General Personal Papers (n.d., 1933-1976)
Series II--Professional Papers (n.d., 1933-1984)
Series III--James Branch Cabell (n.d., 1977-1984)
Series IV--Education of the Heart (n.d., 1654-1982)
Series V--Ellen Glasgow (n.d., 1874-1981)
Series VI--Articles, Lectures, Speeches and Reviews (n.d.)
Series VII--Correspondence (n.d., 1816-1986), Subseries A: Chronological, Subseries B: Alphabetical, Subseries C: Research Correspondence
Series VIII--Ellen Glasgow Society (n.d., 1880-1983)
Series IX--Published materials (n.d., 1961-1985)
Series X--Virginia State Library and Archives Board ( - )
Series XI--James Branch Cabell and Richmond-in-Virginia ( - 1993)
Series XII--Oversize in oversize drawer 25 and box 20
Contents List
- General Personal Papers n.d. 1953-1976
  - Centennial Post 1976 (Box 1)
  - Personal materials (Box 1)
  - Poe Museum Material, n.d. 1976 (Box 1)
  - Richmond (Box 1)
  - St. Christopher's Newspapers; Annual Reports 1933-1938, 1977, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Will of Emily Clark Balch 1953 (Box 1)
- Professional Papers, n.d. 1933-1984
  - Annuaire 1965 (Box 1-a)
  - Association Internationale Des Docteurs (Lettres) 1955-1984 (Box 1-a)
  - Bulletin of Randolph Macon College 1953-1983 (Box 1-a)
  - Centre Roland de Jouvenel (Box 1-a)
  - Fulbright Scholarship--Soviet Union 1984 (Box 1-a)
  - Reception 1966 (Box 1-a)
  - Southern Literature Symposium 1980 (Box 1-a)
  - Virginia Writer's Club, n.d. (Box 1-a)
- James Branch Cabell 1977-1984
  - After the James Branch Cabell Period (Box 2)
  - Book Sellers, n.d. 1977, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Cabell as Prospero, Wylie as Miranda in Richmond, Va (Box 2)
  - Cabell Poems to Gabriella Moncure (Box 2)
  - Cabell related Correspondence, n.d. 1979-1980, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Cabell research material (Box 2)
  - Cabell without Jurgen (Box 2)
  - Cabell's Game of Hide and Seek (Box 2)
  - Cabell's Hero: Cosmic Rebel (Box 2)
  - Cabell's Richmond Trial (Box 2)
  - Fragmented Cabell, The (Box 2)
  - James Branch Cabell: Centennial Essays (Box 2)
  - James Branch Cabell: Centennial Essays Correspondence 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - James Branch Cabell: Centennial Essays Edited Draft (Box 3)
  - James Branch Cabell: Centennial Essays Edited Draft (Box 3)
  - James Branch Cabell: Centennial Essays Index (Box 3)
  - James Branch Cabell--The Women's Club (Box 4)
  - Richmond and The Reviewer by Elizabeth S. Scott (Box 4)
  - Well-Paid Myths (Box 4)
- Education of the Heart
  - American Edgeworths, The 1970, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Books for Fall and Spring 1977 (Box 4)
  - Dictionary of North Carolina Biography 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Edgeworth Bibliography (Box 4)
  - Edgeworth Family (Box 4)
  - Education of the Heart: Biographical Index 1976 (Box 4)
  - Education of the Heart: Correspondence 1968-1982 (Box 4)
  - Education of the Heart: Draft, edited 1 of 4 (Box 4)
  - Education of the Heart: Draft, edited 2 of 4 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Draft, edited 3 of 4 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Draft, edited 4 of 4 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Manuscript 1 of 3 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Manuscript 2 of 3 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Manuscript 3 of 3 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Original 1 of 4 (Box 5)
  - Education of the Heart: Original 3 of 4 (Box 6)
  - Education of the Heart: Original 4 of 4 (Box 6)
  - Education of the Heart: Proofs 1 of 2 (Box 6)
  - Education of the Heart: Proofs 2 of 2 (Box 6)
  - First American Jewish Families 1654-1977 (Box 6)
  - General Papers and Reviews (Box 6)
  - Graded Classics--The King of the Golden River (Box 6)
  - Index (Box 6)
  - Times Literary Supplement 1977 (Box 6)
- Ellen Glasgow
  - Ancient Law (Box 7)
  - Articles on Ellen Glasgow 1935, 1945, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Articles on Ellen Glasgow--Newspaper (Box 7)
  - Articles on Ellen Glasgow--Newspaper (Box 7)
  - Articles on Ellen Glasgow--New Dominion Life Style (Box 7)
  - Barren Ground (Box 7)
  - Battleground (Box 7)
  - Bennett, Anne Virginia (Box 7)
  - Deliverance, A Romance of the Virginia Tobacco Fields (Box 7)
  - Descendant, The (Box 7)
  - Duke, Frank (Box 7)
  - Ellen Anderson Gohlson Glasgow 1874-1945 (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow and the Art of the Novel (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow: An Essay in Bibliography (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow, James Branch Cabell and Richmond (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow-James Branch Cabell Entente (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow: A Reference Guide: Manuscript 1898-1941 (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow: A Reference Guide: Manuscript 1942-1981 (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow: A Reference Guide: Preface (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Flexible Style (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Novels: Time and Place (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Territory (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia 1951-1954 (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia--Background of her Novels (Box 7)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia--Background of her Novels (Box 9)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia--Background of her Novels (Box 9)
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia Women (Box 9)
  - Finger on the Pulse of Life: Ellen Glasgow's Search for Style (Box 9)
  - Focus on Ellen Glasgow's Use of Virginia Territories in Her Novels (Box 9)
  - General File (Box 9)
  - Glasgow Map Material (Box 9)
  - Glasgow Research material (Box 9)
  - Guest Book-Glasgow House (Box 9)
  - Hall, G.K. (Box 9)
  - Happy Birthday, Miss Ellen! (Box 9)
  - Louisa County (Box 10)
  - Mill and Old Church (Box 10)
  - Notes (Box 10)
  - Phases of an Inferior Planet (Box 10)
  - Romance of a Plain Man (Box 10)
  - Romantic Comedians (Box 10)
  - Sheltered Image (Box 10)
  - Sheltered Life, The (Box 10)
  - Six Months with Ellen Glasgow in Virginia (Box 10)
  - Tutwiler, Mrs (Box 10)
  - Two Biographical Notes on Ellen Glasgow (Box 10)
  - Vein of Iron (Box 10)
  - Virginia (Box 10)
  - Voice of the People (Box 10)
  - Wilkins (Ruth Jones) Papers 1 of 2 (Box 10)
  - Wilkins (Ruth Jones) Papers 2 of 2 (Box 10)
- American Literary Scholarship: A Review
  - American Literary Scholarship: A Review (Box 10)
  - Another Opinion of Ingenue Among the Lions (Box 10)
  - Barren Ground: A Classic Revisited (Box 10)
  - Bond That Held (Box 10)
  - Child's Collection Miller (Box 10)
  - Deep and Loving Heart (Box 10)
  - Elinor Wylie and Richmond (Box 10)
  - Henry Sydnor Harrison: A Centennial Appreciation (Box 10)
  - Modern Poetry (Box 10)
  - Reception of Two Black Artists in Mid-1920s Richmond (Box 10)
  - Russian related Memorabilia (Box 10)
  - Scholarship and Teaching (Box 11)
  - Speeches (Box 11)
  - Symbolic Unity of The Heart is a Lonely Hunter (Box 11)
  - Tennessee Williams and the Tragic Tradition (Box 11)
  - Van Vechten Pose: Mark Lutz and Gertrude Stein (Box 11)
  - Virginians: Lives and Literature (Box 11)
  - Williamsburg Public Library Speech (Box 11)
- Correspondence
  - Chronological
    - Correspondence, n.d. 1956-1969 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1974-1978 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1982 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1983 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1984-1990 (Box 12)
  - Alphabetical
    - Andrews, Edna 1985-1986 (Box 13)
    - Bickers, William 1979 (Box 13)
    - Cabell, Margaret Freeman and Ballard, n.d. 1956-1968 (Box 13)
    - Calisch, Edith 1974-1975 (Box 13)
    - Carroll, Roger Hunt, n.d. 1974-1980 (Box 13)
    - Carroll, Roger Hunt 1986-1988 (Box 13)
    - Cherry, Kenneth 1976-1977 (Box 13)
    - Childs, Rives 1966-1973 (Box 13)
    - Clark, Josephine Glasgow, n.d. 1973-1975 (Box 13)
    - Cook, Martha 1980-1982 (Box 13)
    - Davis Paxton 1989 (Box 13)
    - Davis, Richard Beale 1977-1980 (Box 13)
    - Diakonova, Nina 1984-1990 (Box 13)
    - Duke, Maurice 1968-1982 (Box 13)
    - Ekman, Barlero 1978-1980 (Box 13)
    - Flora, Joseph 1972-1984 (Box 13)
    - Free, Ann 1979-1981 (Box 14)
    - Freudenberg, Anne 1976-1986 (Box 14)
    - Gaskin, J.R. 1979 (Box 14)
    - Gatlin, Judith 1975-1979 (Box 14)
    - Giacomini, Lynwood 1972-1981 (Box 14)
    - Godshalk, William 1968-1974 (Box 14)
    - Hartman, Harry 1967 (Box 14)
    - Hibino, Michael 1980 (Box 14)
    - Holman, Hugh 1969-1974 (Box 14)
    - Hood, Thomas 1979 (Box 14)
    - Inge, Thomas 1969-1984 (Box 14)
    - Hook Andrew 1980 (Box 14)
    - Jones, Howard 1974-1979 (Box 14)
    - Kelly, William 1973-1975 (Box 14)
    - Kellner, Bruce, n.d. 1975-1983 (Box 14)
    - Kovalev, Yuri V 1985-1988 (Box 14)
    - Lewis, George, n.d. 1970-1971 (Box 14)
    - McDowell, Fred 1974-1976 (Box 14)
    - Karl, Moreland 1971-1975 (Box 14)
    - Morton, Tim 1974-1975 (Box 14)
    - Myer, Elizabeth 1980 (Box 14)
    - Norfleet, Fillmore 1919, 1977-1982 (Box 14)
    - Penninger, Elaine 1973-1975 (Box 14)
    - Peple, Edward 1969-1984 (Box 14)
    - Raper, J.R. 1974-1983 (Box 15)
    - Roberts, Marguerite 1919-1976 (Box 15)
    - Roberts, Marguerite 1919-1976 (Box 15)
    - Ronson, Ethel n.d. 1970-1978 (Box 15)
    - Rothman, Julius 1967-1971 (Box 15)
    - Rouse, Blaire 1965-1981 (Box 15)
    - Rubin, Louis 1959-1985 (Box 15)
    - Schlegel, Dorothy 1972 (Box 15)
    - Schmidt, Jan 1978-1982 (Box 15)
    - Sharogradskaya, Anna 1984-1990 (Box 15)
    - Sharokava, Eugenia 1984-1987 (Box 15)
    - Shield, Asa 1979-1981 (Box 15)
    - Simpson, Bill 1978-1980 (Box 15)
    - Slatten, Richard 1984 (Box 15)
    - Smylie, James 1975-1976 (Box 15)
    - Tolochin, Igor 1984-1990 (Box 16)
    - Tolochin, Nina 1984-1991 (Box 16)
    - Trigg, Emma, n.d. (Box 16)
    - Tutwiler, Colonel Carrington, n.d. 1974-1981 (Box 16)
    - Wang, Arthur 1978-1984 (Box 16)
    - White III, Luther 1972-1975 (Box 16)
    - Wilkins, Elliot 1974-1982 (Box 16)
    - Williams, Peyton 1974-1977 (Box 16)
    - Woodward, Harry 1975 (Box 16)
    - Woodbridge, Annie 1978-1981 (Box 16)
    - Various Correspondence Concerning Publishing 1977-1978 (Box 16)
  - Research Correspondence
    - Bennett, Anne Virginia, n.d. 1933-1953 (Box 16a)
    - Edgeworth, Maria to Rachel Lazarus 1816-1838 (Box 16a)
    - Glasgow, Ellen, Marjorie K. Rawlings and James Branch Cabell, n.d. 1909-1945 (Box 16a)
    - Glasgow, Ellen to MKR 1939-1944 (Box 16a)
    - Glasgow, Ellen to Hunter Stagg 1944 (Box 17)
    - Lutz, Mark 1934-1936 (Box 17)
    - Lutz, Mark to Bruce Kellner, n.d. 1967 (Box 17)
    - Stagg, Hunter and Gertrude Stein 1923-1941 (Box 17)
    - Williams, Frances L. To Ellen Glasgow 1935 (Box 17)
- Ellen Glasgow Society 1880-1983
  - Articles, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Autograph, n.d. 1880 (Box 17)
  - By-Laws (Box 18)
  - Copy for Newsletter, n.d. 1953-1975 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, n.d. 1975-1983 (Box 18)
  - General Organization 1974-1980 (Box 18)
  - Membership, n.d. 1978-1980 (Box 18)
  - Mary Baldwin College Symposium 1973-1980 (Box 18)
  - MLA Seminar 1975-1980 (Box 18)
  - Newsletter-Comment 1980 (Box 18)
  - Seminar, n.d. 1976-1978 (Box 18)
- Published Materials 1961-1985
  - Brochures and Pamphlets 1964-1985 (Box 19)
  - Down East 1974 (Box 19)
  - Newsletter of the Society for the Study of Southern Literature (Box 19)
  - Newsletter of the Society for the Study of Southern Literature (Box 19)
  - Poetry (Box 19)
  - Southern Literature Information (Box 19)
  - Southern Literature Information 1961 (Box 19)
  - Virginia Verse (Box 19)
- Virginia State Library and Archives Board
  - Notes and Memoranda 1990 (Box 19)
- James Branch Cabell and Richmond-in-Virginia
- Oversize
  - Ellen Glasgow's Virginia map by Ruth Jones Wilkins (Box 20)
  - News Leader article on map 12 December 1951 (Box 20)
  - Engraved Block of map (Box 20)
  - Four photographs of Josephine Glasgow Clark (Box 21)
    Four photographs of Josephine Glasgow Clark, niece of Ellen Glasgow. Two of these are postcard images, one of which also shows her mother,Annie Glasgow clark (Mrs. Frank Tarleton Clark). Both of these postcard images were taken in Atlantic City. It was on this trip to Atantlic City where Annie Glasgow Clark had a stroke and died.
  - Obituaries for Josephine Glasgow Clark (Box 21)
    Two obituaries, one written by Edgar MacDonald and the other from the Richmond Times-Dispatch, April 5, 1984.
  - Ellen Glasgow Festival Posters 1983 (Oversize 25)
  - Video-Tape Richmond: Historic Sights and Haunts (RG 70) (Oversize 25)